[Music]
markdown inline formatting and this is
what most people think about when they
pick up markdowns you may have figured
out um in fact most people's first
exposure particularly if you're watching
me on YouTube or twitch has been using
markdown to create italics or bold in
Discord or slack or something like that
and and that use of markup which is
markdown not always is probably the most
common use of it now I did this kind of
backwards we did headings and blocks
first and then we did what most people
will know uh this inline formatting sort
of last but order doesn't really matter
let's get into it so what is what is how
do you make a a bold thing how do you
make something bold and um this is one
of those areas where there's much
disagreement um uh actually I don't know
if the disagreement is right
word um so let's do this I this this one
right here this thing with blocks MD
blocks is its own document I tried to
keep it separate on purpose let's go
ahead and make a new one for you don't
have to do this but you know you can do
this your own
way um we're going to make a new file
and this one we're going to call MD
inline and inline is is you know the
right name here
MD uh go ahead and commit the changes so
we get a new file
um all right so let's let's actually do
this let's click on edit over
here and I'm going to zoom in a little
bit all right so so this is pretty darn
easy uh so a
single single uh star
asteris
asterisk um for bold I'm sorry for
italic
n is it bold or italic it's actually
um now this actually you know what's
funny I just realizing this is a little
bit
different okay let me let me I'll tell
you the way that I would do it and then
you can
decide
um I I'm just going to show you just
going to show you double uh star for
bold we're going to get some
disagreement here and I want to have a
nice happy debate about this with my
community
um could to do markdown L Tech you can
do math yeah yeah let we'll talk about
that later guys we're going to talk
we're just talking about italics and
inline stuff right now we'll talk about
that other stuff later it's good stuff
to talk about though so three if you
don't remember
anything uh
three4 bold SL
italic and so if you don't remember
anything else you can remember this and
you can just change the number of
stars
um leave it it's it's extremely
problematic though so for example
slack slack uses underscore for
italic uh slack uses
underscore for
italic right in fact you can't use a
single star slack uses bold it it slack
uses a single
star uh slack uses a single
star for bold I don't know why they did
that
but uh unlike mark
down I don't know why they did that it
makes me
why why did they have to divert from the
standard I mean really did they really
have to do
that um but as you can see it's getting
preview here kind of sort sort of for
you um but I mean if you
want to sort of teach your fingers to do
the same thing I would stick with
underscore for
italic um and I would stick with the
singer single star I would do double
star for bold and then if then when
you're in slack just remember to only
put one
it's annoying I know it's annoying right
uh for many years when I taught this to
people at skill stack I said just just
vary the number of stars right one two
and three um that is kind of easy to
remember this is also another reason
that
um
um don't mix uh up your bulleted
lists so this is another gotcha right
um you know this is a list
item and this is another reason probably
to use dashes for for that kind of
thing um let's go look at this one as
you can
see see that it didn't make it uh it
made it it's like waiting around for a
thing if I put it there you know so just
know that um it's probably easier to use
Dash as re bulleted list items we talked
about that because don't mix up let's
see you could say don't and then you can
make this um italic like
this
um U markdown uh get up player markdown
has prevented the use of underscores in
identifiers because underscore is taken
for other things underscore is kind of
problematic for that reason so I tend to
to not use it but that's one of the
things you can
do um
so anyway that that's kind of a that's
kind of the major ones um and then then
you have the last inline
formatter uh the it's called verbatim or
code um this is
um uh pre-formatted
uh you know or
mono or code depending
on what you want to call
it it's up to you but you can see it it
already shows you kind of in the
preview um you can sometimes mix them um
but I'm going to say right here
avoid uh mixing
formats uh
whenever
whenever possible since not all render
support it
uh support mixing what do I mean by that
so so like this um uh I am
italic and you could say I am
really
metallic
right and maybe put the put an
exclamation point on
there and you see that it didn't
work h uh that's wrong right that is
that is not supported by
GitHub um it's just one of the many
places so strictly
speaking this right here should have
been syntax as bold
italic uh but it turned out not to do
that um colors are a formatting thing
and you know the formatting that does
exist in Pand and markdown is meant to
be semantic formatting and we're going
to get into that when we get into the
HTML 5 specification uh the B and the I
Bolden italic are still valid HTML 5 uh
because of semantic uh use of Bolden
italic not necessarily for
formatting um and so but but it's very
it's fair to say that um bold and italic
in markdown are strictly speaking for
formatting um now I personally have
added semantic meaning to my version of
markdown so that I if I use bold for
something it's because it's a term and I
want to look up those terms by searching
for anything that's bold in my code base
that is one of the advantages of using
semantic mark down but that's up to you
and that's not quite out of scope here
um so um see so this this is just an
example of why mixing formatting doesn't
work um that is it my friends that that
is all there is to formatting there is
really not much more to formatting um
there there are some extensions uh to
formatting that is basic markdown
formatting um there are other inline
elements for inline formatting people
ask all the time well what about
footnotes what
about uh you know super case and all of
that we can do those but they are not
part of the standard so
you will not hey chaotic you will not
necessarily get them all the time uh let
me give you an example of one of them
that I don't even know if it's supported
um uh other
extensions uh definitely uh exist but
they are extensions and I I want to make
sure a sythesized extension here um I
want this to be italic see that's going
to be
italic so
um one of the extensions is um here we
can put
um uh one like
that and oh wait it doesn't it doesn't
support it that's
interesting uh I wonder if that's uh I
did it wrong I think it has to be a tag
right I think this is it I think this is
it nope that's not
it I don't know how to do superscript I
know pandoc supports it but I guess this
one doesn't so so this is not a good a
good good one to do I let's let's just
leave it at that if you want to know the
extensions look them up for your thing
the only thing you can reliably use in
markdown for inline formatting is bold
bold italic H bold italic bold italic
and pre-formatted that's it there's
nothing else that's where we're going to
end the video there there are a lot of
other you know we're going to going to
do links next okay but that's all that's
all I don't anything else beyond that is
not covered by anything close to the
standard specification so I'm going to
just end there it's really hard but I'm
just going to tell you that and there's
been a lot of other things invented but
that stay with that and you'll be good
okay